Good morning. Today's דף daf is פט, peh-tet, 89. We pick up
on the bottom of פח עמוד ב, peh-chet amud-bet, last two lines,
four five lines, whatever. We are dealing with an issue... the משנה
mishna discussed that if a person is injured by a woman who
is a married woman, then he's sort of in tough luck because
I mean if he injures her he has to pay but if
he's injured by her she doesn't have any money to pay with
so she owes him the money but she'll have to pay him
later. So we're slowly building up to getting back to that, but
it started by this discussion about a case of a mother who
before her death gave a gift of her property to her son
in order so that her husband would not inherit her and then
the money would property would be divided amongst many sons, not all
of whom were her sons.
And the question was whether she had a right to do that,
whether that was a legitimate gift because that was property of נכסי
מלוג, nichsei milug, property that she owned but because she was married
and even though she had title to it, her husband had the
right to benefit from it. I think this is in the fancy
lingo legal language this is called a right of usufruct which is
the right to benefit from the פירות, peirot, to get the sort
of to reap the benefit from it
even though you don't have the title to it. And the question
is so the woman has a קנין הגוף, kinyan haguf, she has
title. The husband has קנין פירות, kinyan peirot, the right to the
fruit.
If קנין פירות כקנין הגוף דמי, kinyan peirot ke-kinyan haguf dami, if
his right to benefit from it and to get the fruit and
to get the sort of the profit from it make him like
an owner even though he doesn't technically have title in order to
block the sale? That's the question. Can a husband block the wife's
sale or wife's gift of her property, of her נכסי מלוג? nichsei
milug? And the גמרא Gemara tries to bring a proof to this
from a case a similar case about a father and a son.
That the father gave property to a son or whatever, I don't
remember offhand how that worked out, but the basic point was the
son had title to property that he had gotten from his father,
and the father retained the right of the fruit, the פירות. peirot.
And can the son give it to somebody else?
And that was the discussion. If the son gave it to somebody
and then the son died before the father died, would the sale
still be binding? Because is the son able to actually transfer title
even though right now he does not have the right of the
fruit? Can he actually fully transfer title right now? That was the
question. And so רבי ירמיה בר אבא Rabbi Yirmiyah bar Abba said
yes he can, that's the way we watch the particular משנה mishna
that we have in בבא בתרא Bava Batra and therefore that proves
that the father's קנין פירות kinyan peirot is not כקנין הגוף דמי,
ke-kinyan haguf dami, the father's right to the fruit is not like
he has title and cannot block the son's sale. And in parallel
the husband's title to the קנין פירות kinyan peirot is not like
a קנין הגוף kinyan haguf and cannot block the wife's gift to
her son. Okay, so that was the proof. So let's pick up
from well let me read a little bit, and let's pick up
from הדרוה קמיה דרב יהודה, hadruha kamei de-Rav Yehuda, the last narrow
line of פח עמוד ב. peh-chet amud-bet. So they reported this to
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda because they knew he said the woman actually
is not allowed to... the gift that the woman made to her
son was not binding. So they reported to רב יהודה Rav Yehuda
what רבי ירמיה בר אבא Rabbi Yirmiyah bar Abba said. אמר להו,
amar lehu, he said back to them: הכי אמר שמואל, hachi amar
Shmuel, here's what שמואל Shmuel said. זו אינה דומה למשנתנו. zo einah
doma le-mishnateinu.
No, our case of the wife trying to gift property is not
like the case of this משנה mishna about the father and the
son and the son trying to sell property that he has title.
מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, what's the reason? אמר רב יוסף, amar Rav
Yosef, בשלמא אי תני איפכא, bi-shlama i tni ipcha,
had the משנה mishna about the father and the son been the
reverse case הכותב נכסיו לאביו, hakotev nechasav le-aviv,
that the son gave property title to his father and the son
retained the right for the fruit and then the father tried to
transfer title, איכא למשמע מינה דקנין פירות לאו כקנין הגוף דמי, ika
le-mishma minah de-kinyan peirot lav ke-kinyan haguf dami, then it would've been
a good proof that if the person with title is able to
transfer it and the person with the fruit can't block it, that's
telling the person with the fruit is not like an owner, does
not have the ability to block the sale. That would have been
exactly like the case here by the wife.
אלא השתא דתני הכותב נכסיו לבנו, ella hashata de-tni hakotev nechasav li-vno,
that it's the son who now has the title and he is
trying to transfer it, משום דראוי ליורשו הוא, mishum de-ra'uy le-yorsho hu,
maybe the reason the son is able to do it is maybe
the general rule is that the person who has the fruit is
considered an owner and can block the sale. But the reason in
the father and son case the father can't block the sale is
that the son will eventually get the fruit anyway when the father
dies, the son will get the fruit and therefore the son is
in a more empowered position to actually transfer. So maybe the reason
he can transfer title is because even his rights to the fruit
are already there in potential. Okay, and that's not really necessarily the
same case with the wife and the husband. The wife and husband
it depends who's going to die when or whatever etc. to whether
the wife will ever regain her rights to the fruit. But by
the son, he will naturally gain the right to the fruit, and
therefore that puts him in a more empowered position. So maybe it's
not a general proof that the person with the title can transfer
and the person with the fruit cannot block. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says one minute. אמר ליה Amar Lei, אביי Abaye *Amar lei
Abaye*, אביי Abaye *Abaye* said back in, אתו ברא ירת אבא אבא
לא ירת ברא *atu bera yaras abba abba lo yaras bera*? Wait
a minute he said, it wouldn't have mattered which way we were
talking about, whether the father wrote it to the son or the
son wrote it to the father, because either way it's you know
even if it's the son writing to the father, it's possible that
the father will inherit from the son. Now don't worry about that
too much, the real point is the next point. He says אלא
ella *ela*, what would be the reason a son would write over
his property to his father? I mean you know, if even he
doesn't have to give his property to father, if he dies but
he doesn't have any kids then his father will inherit it. Okay,
so what's the reason he is writing it to his father? It
must be לאברוחי לנכסי מבריה אתי *le'avruchei lenichsei mibrei ati*.
He's actually no because he actually has kids and he doesn't want
his kids to inherit. He wants the property to go to his
father. Okay, so that's all lead up to make this next point,
and here's really the next point. What's the reason the father is
gifting the property to his son? His son's going to inherit him
anyway. And if he's gifting the property but holding on to the
fruit, the son gets no benefit right now. If he just transfers
title and the father holds on to the fruit, what good does
it do the son? He's getting no benefit now and eventually he'll
get the benefit when the father dies, but he's going to inherit
his father anyway when the father dies, right? So what good does
it do the son to have the title now if the benefit
will only come when the father dies? So there is a good,
the good is if there are other sons, right? So אלא *ela*
and that's the key point. So הכא נמי *hacha nami* so here
too לאברוחי לנכסי מאחוה אתי *le'avruchei lenichsei me'achvei ati*. The reason the
father is transferring title to the son even though the son doesn't
get any benefit yet is to prevent the brothers, his other sons,
from getting this piece of property.
So therefore what? Therefore he says you can't say the reason the
son is in a more empowered position. You can't say the son
is in a more empowered position here than the wife because he's
anyway going to inherit his father. Because אביי *Abaye* says what's the
scenario? The scenario that a father is doing this is if there
are brothers and he wants to keep the property away from the
brothers. So the son is not going to inherit would not naturally
inherit this whole property anyway. He'd inherit a piece of it, right?
So he wouldn't inherit all of it. So you can't say that
he eventually he's going to get the fruit anyway and that gives
him a stronger position. Because without this special arrangement, he would not
get the fruit, he would not get all the fruit, he'd only
get a part of it. And nevertheless, he's able to fully transfer
title. So if the son can fully transfer title even though the
father holds on to the פירות peiros *peirot* and even though he
would not naturally have gotten all the פירות peiros. *peirot*, then the
wife should also be able to transfer title. So we're back to
our argument. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says אלא פשיטא מאי איכא
למימר *ela peshita mai ika l'meimar* what's the reason the case of
the wife is not similar to the case of the father and
the son? משום דתקנתא דאושא *mishum detakanata de'Usha*. You're right, in principle
it is the same and in principle if we rule like ריש
לקיש *Reish Lakish*, which we do, that קנין פירות Peiros. לאו כקנין
הגוף *kinyan peirot lav kekinyan haguf*, the one who has rights to
the fruit is not like an owner, then the one with the
title should be able to transfer title even if the other person
has the fruit. You're 100% right in principle. But there's a special
תקנה takkanah *takana* in אושא Usha *Usha*, which was one of the
places where the סנהדרין *Sanhedrin* moved after כרם ביבנה *Kerem Beyavneh*. Whatever,
there's a special תקנה takkanah. *takana* that they actually gave the husband
more rights than a person in this arrangement would normally have. And
the husband actually is able to block the wife's sale. Okay, דאמר
רבי יוסי בר חנינא Rebbi Yosi bar Chanina *de'amar Rabi Yosi bar
Chanina* באושא התקינו *be'Usha hitkinu* in אושא Usha *Usha* they established האשה
שמכרה בנכסי מלוג בחיי בעלה *ha'isha she'machra benichsei milug be'chayei ba'alah* exactly
this discussion, a woman who's trying to sell the title to her
property while her husband's alive even though she has the title, the
husband has the right to the fruit, ומתה *ve'meisah* if she dies,
okay now what would normally happen if she died and hadn't sold
the title? The husband would inherit her. But now she has transferred
the title. באושא התקינו *be'Usha hitkinu* in אושא *Usha* they said tough
luck that she transferred the title, הבעל מוציא מיד הלקוחות *haba'al motzi
miyad halakochos*, the husband is still going to inherit her, the husband
will get that from the
purchasers, the sale will not go through. The husband basically can block
the sale. He probably would have to give the money back of
course, but but
particularly in the case of a gift like here, the mother tried
to gift it to her son to keep it away from her
husband and from her husband's other sons, okay, and that does not
work. When she dies her husband still inherits her. The husband effectively
blocks the sale. Yes.
What's the chronology between that תקנה takana *takana* and this dispute between
שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* and רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan, *Rabi Yochanan*?
I was going to ask the same question. So אושא *Usha* is
early, אושא *Usha* is Mishnaic. Yeah, exactly.
So they would have known about this.
So how did they not know it? Yeah, that's a good question.
So but רבי Rebbi יוסי Yosi בר חנינא *Rabi Yosi bar Chanina*
again I don't know exactly his dates but but you know that's
like a question. That's his, like you're right, I mean I was
wondering that, like that's his claim of what they were מתקן *metaken*.
talking about אושא. Did anybody agree to that? I mean שמואל Shmuel
presumably, now with שמואל's Shmuel tradition, presumably רבי ירמיה Rebbi Yirmiya did
not have that tradition. You're right. So you know, it wasn't like
they had to check the congressional record. It was like some people
had the tradition that that was תקנת אושא takkanas Usha and presumably
he did not.
Presumably שמואל Shmuel. would have lived like a century after the אושא
because by משנה Mishnah times they'd already left אושא and moved to
ציפורי Tzipori where רבי was.
Right, right, right. But the question is רבי יוסי Yosi בר חנינא
what generation he is, which I don't know. I can try to
see. I'm not good generally in terms of the exact dates but
יוסי Yosi... or יוסי or יוסי...
You will never make it in JTS.
I know. I have to tell you I was once at like,
this was a funny story. Anyway,
Jewish אמורא Amora sage, second generation of אמוראים. Amoraim. So to
second generation, so I mean, that would be after רב, Rav, that
would be like after, after or around the time of שמואל. Shmuel,
At the end of the second generation. בין דור שני ושלישי של
אמוראים.
Bein
dor sheini vishlishi shel Amoraim.
רבי יוחנן, he was his, what's his, what's his רב. rav. So
that actually, so שמואל, Shmuel so you know, it's interesting. שמואל Shmuel
says it's not similar to שמואל Shmuel also knows of תקנת אושא,
takkanas Usha, but anyway, this idea of תקנת אושא takkanas Usha was
only said explicitly, right, I mean, you know, you know, after שמואל
Shmuel had said his אמר רב. amar Rav. So it's, you know,
clearly not everybody had this tradition.
Is there a reason for the תקנה that's given or I mean...
Well, the basic reason is sort of like an איבה eiva type
of a תקנה. The same reason they instituted, I mean, there's a
general question about why they instituted that, about the husband inheriting his
wife. Is that דאורייתא de-Oraisah or דרבנן? de-Rabbanan? So, but you know,
I mean חז"ל Chazal sort of set up in כתובות Kesuvos the
whole sort of set of arrangements about here are the husband's responsibilities,
here are the rights he has to his wife's property or his
wife's earnings or so on. So presumably, you know, it's like they
felt it was needed to create that sort of balance in those
types of financial arrangements, you know.
But, you know, obviously because otherwise a woman could also always, I
guess, I don't know back then, but you know, the way it
would be, a woman could always sort of prevent her husband from
taking the property, right? Make some type of essentially write it into
a trust, make some type of an arrangement to write the whole
thing away, etc., etc. But, so anyway, so that's what they did.
אמר רב אידי בר אבין, Amar Rav Idi bar Avin, אמר רב
אידי בר אבין, amar Rav Idi bar Avin, אף אנן נמי תנינא.
af anan nami tanina. Now we're benching, we are going to get
back to our משנה. Mishnah. We also taught similarly that a woman
cannot gift away or sell away the title to her property, you
know, that the נכסי מלוג. nichsei milog. ומייתי באנו דפלוני שגירושיהן של
אשתו. Umayisi ba'anu depolany shegerusheihen shel ishto.
There's a ברייתא beraisa that witnesses come and say:
We testify that ראובן Reuven divorced his wife שרה Sarah here ונתן
כתובתה venasan kesuvatah and paid her כתובה. kesuvah. Now these are going
to found out to be false witnesses, okay. והרי היא תחתיו ומשמשתו.
Ve-harei hi tachtav u-meshameshashto.
It looks like he's living together with her, it looks like they're
still married, we're telling you that's not true, she's divorced and she
received her כתובה. kesuvah. So what does that- and they're- and they're
going to be lying, עדים זוממין, edim zomemin, they're found out to
be false witnesses. So you have to do to them like they
were trying to do to the other person. Now who were they
trying to hurt? Well, I mean, if the guy was a כהן,
kohein, you could say they tried to hurt him that he can't
remarry his wife, but that's not the point. Okay, the point is
that they're basically trying to hurt her. They're trying to make it
that
there'll be testimony that she received her כתובה, kesuvah, so she'll never
be able to collect her כתובה kesuvah after that, okay. Now,
אין אומרים, ein omrim, and how much do they owe her? So
what would she have collected with the כתובה? kesuvah? She would have
collected the 200 זוז, zuz, which is the face value of the
כתובה, kesuvah, but she would have also taken back any of her
נכסי צאן ברזל, nichsei tzon barzel, the dowry she would have brought
into the property she would have taken out, and the husband would
have lost his right to the פירות Peiros of the property she
already had the title to. Okay, so אין אומרים ישלמו כל כתובתה.
ein omrim yeshalmu kol kesuvatah.
They don't say to them: Now, pay the whole כתובה, kesuvah, pay
the 200 זוז zuz plus the
נכסי מלוג, nichsei milog, plus I guess the right of the פירות.
Peiros You don't say to them that. Why? Because right now, it's
not like she has that money in her pocket right now. Right
now that she's married, right, she might not ever collect her כתובה.
kesuvah. A, she doesn't have the right to that money right now.
B, she might die first and never collect the כתובה. kesuvah. So
how much is her כתובה kesuvah worth? They were trying to make
it that she could never collect her כתובה. kesuvah. So they were
trying to rob her from her right to her כתובה. kesuvah. What
is the value, current value of her כתובה? kesuvah? אלא אין אומרים
ישלמו כל כתובתה, Ela ein omrim yeshalmu kol kesuvatah, pay the whole
כתובה, kesuvah, אלא טובת הנאה, ela tovas hana'ah, הנאת כתובתה, hana'as kesuvatah,
the benefit of the value of her כתובה, kesuvah, which means the
market value of her כתובה. kesuvah. It's not its full face value,
but what would have been the value that she could have sold
it for on the market? Somebody would have paid for it as
a gamble, right? It's sort of like, you know, buying life insurance
or whatever it is, right, as a gamble, although I guess life
insurance eventually you collect unless the person doesn't die. But you know,
it's a gamble, is she going to die first? is he gonna
die first, is he gonna die first, and so on. How much
would a כתובה Kesubah with a face value of ten thousand dollars
go for in the market? Okay. Now, איזהו טובת הנאת כתובתה, Eizehu
Tovat Hana'as Kesubasah, that's how you would determine its its value. אומדים,
Omdim, you estimate or you assess is really a better word, כמה
אדם רוצה ליתן בכתובתה של זו, Kama Adam Rotze Liten B'kesubasah Shel
Zo, how much is a person willing to pay to buy this
כתובה Kesubah right now on the risk or on the chance that
if she is ארמלון Armalon or נתגרשה, Nisgareshah, she dies first or
divorces her, she'll collect it, ואי מתה, Ve-ee Meisah, but on the
flip side, if she dies, יירשנה בעל, Yerashanah Ba'al, he won't collect
it as the husband will inherit. And that's how you determine what
its face value is, and that's what they were trying to rob
her of.
Now how does this prove that there's such a thing like תקנת
אושא Takanas Usha that would prevent a woman from transferring the title?
גמרא Gemara says simply, אי סלקא דעתך לית ליה תקנת אושא, Ee
Salka Da'itach Leis Lei Takanas Usha, if you don't believe that there's
such a thing as תקנת אושא, Takanas Usha, you believe that a
woman can sell title to her property, so אמאי יירשנה בעל, Amai
Yerashanah Ba'al, so why do we say, well, you know, she can't
collect the full value because she might die or her husband
might,
you know, might inherit from her? תזבין כתובתה לגמרי, Tizbin Kesubasah Legamrei,
let her fully sell her כתובה, Kesubah, at least the נכסי מלוג,
Nichsei Milog, meaning there's one piece of the כתובה Kesubah that is
actually worth its full face value, or close to its full face
value, and that is her נכסי מלוג. Nichsei Milog. She has title
to a hundred acres, okay, that the husband is eating the פירות.
Peiros Now, whatever happens,
she will, like whether she dies first or he dies first or
he divorces her or whatever, she could, if she could sell that
title, so the husband will never inherit it, okay? So why do
we say make it sound like her whole כתובה Kesubah is at
risk whether somebody will get the whole value in the future or
zero? There's a piece of it that somebody could definitely get. What
would that piece of it be that somebody would definitely get? The
title to the נכסי מלוג, Nichsei Milog, which would then and then
he would definitely get the פירות Peiros, once the husband died. It
wouldn't matter who died first,
okay? So you all sort of with me here? Okay. So therefore,
even though that's not the full value of a hundred acres, because
you don't have the right to the פירות Peiros. right now, you're
only gonna get the right to the פירות peiros. once the husband
dies, it's not the same as it's all at risk, okay? You
can def—it has a definite, you know, you can definitely there's a
transfer that value of fully right now and with the
and even if it's not at risk, but with the future getting
of the פירות, you're just not sure when you're going to get
the פירות. So why does it make it sound like the entire
value of the כתובה Kesubah is at risk? So it must be
that there's תקנת אושא Takanas Usha and there's no part of the
כתובה Kesubah that she can sell right now. There's no part that
she will definitely get, you know, regardless of who dies first, okay?
So תזבין כתובתה לגמרי. Tizbin Kesubasah Legamrei. So אמר אביי, Amar Abaye,
no, אם אמר בנכסי מלוג יאמר בנכסי צאן ברזל? Im Amar B'nichsei
Milog Yomar B'nichsei Tzon Barzel? So אביי says, who says we're talking
about the נכסי מלוג? Nichsei Milog?
Maybe you're right. Maybe the נכסי מלוג Nichsei Milog is a part
that actually, you know,
he definitely will get because she can she can't sell it right
now regardless of who dies first, okay? Maybe there is no תקנת
אושא. Takanas Usha. But when the ברייתא Braisa made it sound like
the עדים זוממים, Edim Zomemim, like you know like we're trying to
assess what they made her lose and that it's possible that the
whole כתובה Kesubah was at risk, that's talking about the base two
hundred plus the נכסי צאן ברזל, Nichsei Tzon Barzel, plus the dowry.
Because that stuff is fully the title is in the husband's name,
okay? The husband totally took—he never paid the two hundred, so obviously
it's under his title,
and he totally took title of the dowry. So that's the stuff
that if she dies first, you know, she's not going to collect
any. If she dies first or divorces her, she'll collect in full.
That's the amount that's totally at risk. Is this clear? I'll draw
I'll draw a picture of it.
Now that I have a board, I can use the board. Here's
the husband, here's his wife, okay? So she brings into him property,
okay,
dowry, which
is נכסי צאן ברזל, Nichsei Tzon Barzel,
צאן ברזל, Tzon Barzel, because that's what we say
is iron—I love that term, dowry? No, iron heat. Because she's gonna
take it all back out no matter what happens to it, okay?
This is—this is what we write in the כתובה. Kesubah. דנעלת ליה
מבי אבוה בין בכסף בין בזהב,
D'na'alas Lei M'vei Avuha
Bein B'kesef Bein B'zahav, you know, בין בכסף בין בזהב. Bein B'kesef
Bein B'zahav. We
we assess what's the value, and we say it's מאה וזוקוקין כסף
צרוף. Meah V'zukukin Kesef Tzaruf. Well, actually we
don't. We say שמנו מאה וזוקוקין כסף צרוף Shameinu Meah V'zukukin Kesef
Tzaruf plus the extra hundred of the תוספת. Tosafos. Okay, so we
determine how much money did she give him in dowry? That goes
over, and he now has title to it, okay? And he has
title. Okay, so that's the צאן ברזל. Tzon Barzel. Okay, that, but
if he dies first or divorces her, she takes that full value
out. There's also the 200 which is the base amount which he
has title to which he never paid her to begin with.
Okay. And then there is the here her property
in נכסי מלוג Nikhsei Milug which she has title to but he
gets the fruit. Look at the little fruit. Here's my fruit. Okay.
So he gets the fruit, okay, but she keeps title to that.
All right. Where does the תוספת Tosefet appear in which region? The
תוספת Tosefet is like is also money that he promised her that
he never paid. That would be plus תוספת. Tosefet. Okay. Okay.
So
here, basically all of this if they try to rob her of
her כתובה, Ketubah, they're going to prevent her by saying she was
divorced and she collected it which she didn't. They're going to prevent
her from collecting all of this and from regaining the fruit. Okay.
Let's throw the fruit over to here. Okay. That's the fruit.
Okay. They're going to prevent her from getting all of that. How
much do you set how much this is worth? Well, she might
never get any of that. So how much would a person pay
in the market to get the risk of collecting all of this
depending on who dies first or depending on who gets divorced. Okay.
So that's what it says. The גמרא Gemara says, ah but one
minute, but they were also trying to rob her of the נכסי
מלוג Nikhsei Milug and that actually, you know, if it is if
there is תקנת אושא Takanat Usha so that also something she might
never that she had never has no direct value of right now
at all, right? But if there is a תקנת אושא, Takanat Usha,
then they really were robbing her robbing her because they robbed her
of the ability to sell this right now and to get value
for it, okay, even though it would not have been its full
value because she didn't have the right to fruit. But if there
was no such thing as תקנת אושא, Takanat Usha, these lying עדים
Eidim basically have basically now prevented her from, you know,
from selling that. So the גמרא Gemara answer is no, we're not
talking about נכסי מלוג. Nikhsei Milug. We're talking about all this stuff,
okay, and this is the stuff that that is at risk and
this is the stuff that we have to assess how much would
a person pay. So you really can't deduce from here whether there
is תקנת אושא Takanat Usha or not תקנת
אושא.
Takanat
Usha.
But wouldn't someone gain by all of this? Then then they might
be paid by the husband. Okay.
Or they just don't hate her. Okay. Anyway, all right. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this. I mean, I don't fully get the
whole about well whatever. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this. Okay. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, טובת הנאה, Tovat Hana'ah, this discussion
of the טובת הנאה, Tovat Hana'ah, the how much you pay that's
not the face value but for the, you know, for the possible
benefit or for taking the gamble. So הוה ואתי לידיה נימא בה
מילתא. Hava v'ati l'yadei nima bah milta. Since we're discussing it let's
say something about it. טובת הנאה דאישה הויא. Tovat hana'ah d'isha havya.
Okay, that if the woman actually now that the עדים זוממים Eidim
Zomemim are basically who do they pay? So they pay the wife.
Meaning because yeah because that was her because that's her benefit in
the כתובה Ketubah is טובת הנאה. Tovat Hana'ah. That seems a pretty
obvious point. Of course it's דאישה. D'isha. It's the wife's benefit, you
know, dollar value of the כתובה Ketubah that she has rights to.
דאי סלקא דעתך דבעל הויא, D'ei salka da'atach d'ba'al havya, if you
would if you would think that the husband would get it, לימא
להו עדים, Laima lehu eidim, why can't the עדים Eidim say to
this woman מאי חסידנאך? Mai chasidnach? So what did we make you
lose? You're not the one that lost out anything by us claiming
that she would have collected the whole thing.
אי הות מזבנה לה טובת הנאה, Ei havot mezavna lah tovat hana'ah,
בעל, I'm sorry, I said I read that wrong. Let the עדים
Eidim, say let me start this one more time.
Let I this is not starting about the עדים, Eidim, it's starting
about in general. If a wife were to sell, a wife can't
sell, we just discussed this actual נכסי מלוג Nikhsei Milug because the
husband has rights to the fruit. So she obviously can't sell this
stuff, this is all in her husband's title. But let's say what
she wants to do is she wants to actually sell her כתובה,
Ketubah, right? The wife actually wants to like selling your life insurance
policy. The wife actually not because of the עדים, Eidim סתם Stam
she needs cash, her husband isn't giving her any money, whatever it
is. So she actually sells somebody her כתובה Ketubah and that person
is exactly what we discussed is pays however much it's worth to
take the gamble of collecting all of this. So he says if
the wife sells the כתובה Ketubah for the טובת הנאה, Tovat Hana'ah,
she gets the pocket. Now that seems pretty obvious. Of course it's
her rights that she selling. Okay. So let's just spell it out.
טובת הנאה דאישה הויא. Tovat hana'ah d'isha havya.
דאי סלקא דעתך דבעל הויא, D'ei salka da'atach d'ba'al havya, if she
would to sell her כתובה Ketubah and she'd have to give that
money to her husband, okay, because maybe you think, you know, מה
שקנתה אישה קנה בעלה, Ma shekaneta isha kana ba'alah, so even the
money she gets for selling her כתובה Ketubah she would have to
give to her husband. If you would to think such a thing,
דאי סלקא דעתך דבעל הויא, D'ei salka da'atach d'ba'al havya, לימא להו
עדים, Laima lehu eidim, why can't the עדים eidim say to this
woman מאי חסידנאך? Mai chasidnach? So what were we trying to rob
you of your כתובה? Ketubah? What did we make you lose? What,
what did we make you lose right now? Right now you have
no value from it. אי הוה מזבנת לה לטובת הנאה, ei hava
mezabnas lah letovat hana'ah, even had you sold it and got and
got the the value of the כתובה ketubah that somebody would have
paid, בעל הוה שקיל מינך, ba'al hava shakil minach, your husband would
have taken it from you. So you see that that, I mean
this is again strange reasoning, but since in general we say that
money a woman earns goes to her husband, that that's a value
that doesn't apply if she sells her כתובה. ketubah. The כתובה ketubah
is the one thing that she has rights to. So she sells
her כתובה, ketubah, that would be money she would pocket, and therefore
when the עדים were trying to rob her of her כתובה, ketubah,
they pay her. Okay, moving on. We still have not, אמר רב
שמן
משום דאיכא רווחא דביתא. amar Rav Shaman mishum de'ika revach beisa. רב
שמן Rav Shaman says, not necessarily. Maybe the husband would have pocketed
the money if she would have sold her כתובה, ketubah, but what
but nevertheless, you know, if you put the money in a joint
bank account, not really a joint bank account, his bank account, but
you sold your כתובה ketubah and now you gave more money into
the to your husband, so now the husband's got some more better
cash flow, more money around. So there's more money to be spent
in the household, so there's still an indirect way in which she
benefits even if the money would have transferred to the husband. So
you can't totally prove that she would have pocketed that money. Of
course it still sounds like it, because that still would not be
the amount that she would indirectly benefit would have been less than
the total amount it would have actually been sold for. You know,
so it really does sound like she would be the one that
would pocket, and that's what you would assume. The כתובה ketubah is
the one thing that she has rights to that her husband doesn't,
you know, that's it's really her rights. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara continues.
אמר רבא הלכתא טובת הנאה לאשה. amar Rava hilchasa tovat hana'ah l'isha.
He says the logical thing, like אביי was saying, no, if a
woman sells her כתובה ketubah she gets to pocket the money, ואין
הבעל אוכל פירות. v'ein haba'al ochel peiros. Now, not only that, she
sold her כתובה, ketubah, you know, for this whole risk here, you
know, the face value was ten thousand dollars, but what you were
willing to pay, A was only going to be in the future
you would collect, B there was a risk, so you'll pay three
thousand dollars for it, okay? So she takes that three thousand dollars,
she pockets it. That's point number one. This is not money that
then goes to her husband. Now point number two is, ah, but
maybe we should say, what's the general הלכה halachah about property that
a woman has that she has title to? That's the נכסי מלוג.
nichsei milug. So this three thousand dollars is her property, she has
title to it, she doesn't transfer it to her husband, but let's
say fine, but at least take that money, buy property and have
the husband get the fruit because that's what you do with general
property that a woman has, you know, title to. Right? Or take
the money, put it in some, you know, in some bonds and
let the husband get the interest. Fine, you're right. She sold her
כתובה ketubah for this part of the כתובה, ketubah, she got three
thousand bucks for it. That three thousand bucks she keeps, her husband
doesn't get. Okay, so that means it's a type of נכסי מלוג,
nichsei milug, property she has title to, the husband doesn't take title
but he should still get the פירות. Everybody understands the question? Okay.
Yeah, that money came after she got married?
Right. So that's what the גמרא gemara is going to say. Okay.
So the גמרא gemara says, טובת הנאה לאשה ואין הבעל אוכל פירות.
tovat hana'ah l'isha v'ein haba'al ochel peiros. And the husband does not
get any benefit off of that money. If she puts it in
some interest-bearing account, she keeps the interest, not the husband.
מאי טעמא פירות תיקנו ליה רבנן פירי דפירי לא תיקנו ליה רבנן.
mai ta'ama peiros tiknu leih rabanan peiri d'peiri lo tiknu leih rabanan.
Which basically is this טובת הנאה tovat hana'ah is something that she
got is like a double derivative. It's a derivative benefit she got
from the כתובה ketubah and it's a derivative of the derivative that
he doesn't have. Okay. Now, by the way, it's not true that
there are some types of fruit of fruit the husband does get.
Let's say she brings, you know,
sheep into the marriage
and then the sheep have babies and the babies have babies and
the babies have babies. That the husband does get. That's like a,
you know, let's say like in your, in whatever if you do
have some interest-bearing account, they reinvest the interest, right? So that's a
type of a natural fruit of fruit that the husband does get.
But this type of a thing where the whole thing was like
an unexpected, I don't call it a windfall here, but something that's
not the natural produce outcome of this property that she would sell
it for the טובת הנאה, tovat hana'ah, right, that type of a
fruit, an unexpected fruit, he doesn't get the second-degree benefit from that.
Okay, let's get back to this question of the תקנת אושא takanas
Usha why we're discussing it all together. כי אתא רב פפא ורב
הונא בריה דרב יהושע מבי רב, ki asa Rav Pappa v'Rav Huna
brei d'Rav Yehoshua mibei Rav, when רב פפא Rav Pappa and רב
הונא Rav Huna the son of רב יהושע Rav Yehoshua came from
the house of רב, Rav, אמרי תנינא לתקנת אושא. amri teninan l'takanas
Usha. You know, you can see that clearly this question of whether
there was such a תקנה was in question because A, רבי ירמיה
בר אבא Rabbi Yirmiyah bar Abba didn't know and second of all
why we're trying so hard to prove it. Okay, so he says
we actually can have a משנה mishna that proves תקנת אושא. takanas
Usha. Our משנה, mishna, we're finally going to get back to our
משנה. mishna. העבד והאשה פגיעתן רעה, ha'eved v'ha'isha pegi'atan ra'ah, a woman
and a slave, encountering them is bad business. החובל בהן חייב, hachovel
bahen chayav, that meaning hitting them, encountering them in some type of
a of a physical, you know, like causing injury, if you cause
injury to them you have to pay. והם שחבלו באחרים פטורים, v'heim
shechavlu b'acheirim pturim, but if they They injured other people, they're exempt.
Now, it doesn't mean they're exempt, it means that they don't pay
now, they'll only pay if the slave is freed or the woman
is divorced and they get their own money, which means the woman
when she is married is considered to have no money of her
own. Okay, so he says, why does she have no money of
her own? She's got something she can sell. You know what she
can sell? נכסי מלוג. Nichsei milog. Let her sell her נכסי מלוג,
Nichsei milog, transfer the title. Again, somebody's not going to pay the
full value because he doesn't get the fruit just yet, but let
her sell that and use that to pay for the חבלה. chavalah.
So why does it make it sound like there's absolutely no way
under normal circumstances that a woman has any to get any cash
on hand? So the גמרא gemara says, אי
סלקא דעתך, ee salka daitach, and this is why we had this
whole discussion, אי סלקא דעתך לית לה תקנת אושא, ee salka daitach
let la takanat usha, if you don't believe that there's such a
thing as תקנת אושא, takanat usha, תזבין נכסי מלוג, tazbin nichsei milog,
let her sell the נכסי מלוג, nichsei milog, ותיתן ליה, v'titen ley,
and use that to pay off the guy that she injured. So
clearly it must be there's no way she can sell her נכסי
מלוג. nichsei milog. So that seems to be a pretty good proof.
But the גמרא gemara says one minute. ולטעמך u'ltamecha according to your
reasoning, נהי נמי דאיתא תקנת אושא, nehi nami de'isa takanat usha, fine,
you have תקנת אושא, takanat usha, ולא מצי מזבנה לגמרי, v'lo mati
mazbina lagamre, and she can't sell them לגמרי, legamre, תזבין נכסי מלוג
בטובת הנאה, tazbin nichsei milog b'tovat hana'ah, ותיתן ליה. v'titen ley.
There's still some way she can get money. How could she get
money? She can, fine, you can't transfer title. You know what you
can still do? I can sell you, again, the טובת הנאה, tovat
hana'ah, the risk. I can basically sell you, Charlie, here you are,
I'm going to sell you, you're not going to get title right
now of this because I'm not allowed to, but if my husband
dies first or he divorces me, I will get back my נכסי
מלוג nichsei milog and I'll get all of this stuff, let's not
forget all of this stuff, okay, and I can actually get some
cash on hand right now, how, just through this discussion, טובת הנאה?
tovat hana'ah? I can sell you the future rights that you will
get to the, you know, that I'll get in my נכסי מלוג
nichsei milog though I have nothing right now. But if my husband
dies first or he divorces me, I'll get all of this and
my נכסי מלוג nichsei milog back, and you can, you would pay
me money to have the right to get that, you know, at
that future time, that possibility. So why am I not forced to
sell all of that and use that money to pay for the
guy I injured? So the גמרא gemara says,
בטובת הנאה ותיתן ליה b'tovat hana'ah v'titen ley and pay the guy
she injured. גמרא gemara says no, that she can't do. הא מני
רבי מאיר היא, ha-mani Rabbi Meir hi, דאמר אסור לו לאדם שישהא
את אשתו אפילו שעה אחת בלא כתובה. de-amar asur lo l'adam she'isheh
et ishto afilu sha'ah achat belo ktubah. A man cannot stay with
his wife even for one minute without a כתובה. ktubah. So if
I am selling my כתובה ktubah to somebody else, I no longer
have rights to my כתובה. ktubah. If my husband divorces me, I
don't collect. So Rabbi Meir would say then you're not allowed to
stay married to your husband, you can't stay married without having, without
your, without having your כתובה. ktubah. So the גמרא gemara says one
minute, that doesn't make sense.
וטעמא מאי, v'ta'ama mai, כדי שלא תהא קלה בעיניו להוציאה. keda'i shelo
tehei kala b'einav l'hotziah. גמרא gemara says one minute, why does רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir say that you can't, a man can't be married
to his wife without a כתובה? ktubah? Because he says without a
כתובה ktubah it will be too easy to divorce the wife, there'll
be no financial consequence on his account. Remember he could do, unilaterally
divorce the wife, one day he gets upset with her, he just
writes her a גט get and throws it at her, you know,
it doesn't cost him any cash. So if he has to pay
out a כתובה, ktubah, he's going to slow down. Okay, so therefore
that's why it's forbidden because we want to make sure that the
husband does not too easily divorce his wife. So the גמרא gemara
says if that's the only reason, it doesn't matter who he's paying
the money to. I sold my כתובה ktubah to Charlie here, my
husband's not going to easily divorce me because he won't have to
pay me the money but he'll have to pay Charlie the money.
So why should that, why should I not be able to sell
my כתובה ktubah to Charlie? Okay. So the גמרא gemara says הכא
לא מגרש לה. hacha lo magareish lah. Here
he's not going to divorce her
either, דאם מגרש לה אתו הנך דזבני גבו לה דכתובתה מיניה.
d'im magareish lah atu hanach
d'zavnei gavu lah d'ktubatah minei. Okay, so we still haven't explained why
the woman can't sell her כתובה ktubah and use that money to
pay the person she injured. They're telling me oh she can't sell
נכסי מלוג, nichsei milog, so this proves תקנת אושא. takanat usha. Forget
all of that. Why can't she pay the guy she injured by
selling off her כתובה ktubah for its potential future value? One minute,
so the גמרא gemara says אלא טובת הנאה מילי נינהו. ela tovat
hana'ah mili ninhu. Here's why she can't sell the טובת הנאה, tovat
hana'ah, the potential future, because that's only an abstract thing, that's only
a right, it's not a real ownership of property, it's only a
future right. ומילי לא משתעבדי, u-mili lo mishtabdi, and things that are
abstract rights, the person she injured does not have a lien on,
does not have an ability to demand that she sells rights. You
know, he can collect property, but this is just a right. So
the גמרא Gemara says, what does that make sense? אלמה לא, alamah
lo, ומילי דמזדבני בדינרי נינהו. v'mili d'mizdabni b'dinarei ninhu.
It's words, meaning it's abstract rights, but that are sold for hard
cash. You know, it's something she has of value. Who cares if
conceptually it's abstract? Something she has of value, she injured this guy,
she should be forced to sell whatever she has of value to
pay this guy.
So the גמרא Gemara says אלא משום דשמואל. ela mishum de'shmuel. Fine,
here's why we can't tell her you have to sell your כתובה
ktubah to pay the guy you injured. Shmuel says. דאמר שמואל המוכר
שטר חוב לחברו וחזר ומחלו מחול ואפילו יורש מוחל. D'amar Shmuel hamocher
shtar chov l'chavero v'chazar umachalo machul v'afilu yoresh mochel.
If you sell a debt to somebody or
not a debt, what's it called, it is a debt, it's money
you're owed. You have a document that somebody owes you
money, okay, so David you owe me a thousand dollars and I'm
going to now sell it to Charlie for five hundred because he's
not sure you can actually get David to pay it, its risky,
whatever, you're not going to pay full face value. Just like this
case which is essentially the woman and the husband, right? It's money
he owes her under certain circumstances, she's going to sell it that
somebody might be able to collect in the future. Okay, it's a
debt basically. Now, Charlie is going to come to David to collect.
Okay, but I'm going to say to David, David just pay me
five hundred dollars and I'll be מוחל mochel the thousand dollar debt.
Okay, and I'm actually able to do that. Now that sounds crazy
because nobody would be stupid enough to actually buy this document because
I can always just be מוחל mochel it and תוספות Tosafot deals
with that but the logic of it is, the mechanism of it
is, the גמרא Gemara had a very hard time sort of sort
of understanding, but sort of dealing with the reality, how do you
transfer a debt? Okay, because if you understand the debt as somewhat
personal, so David owes me the money, how can now he owe
Charlie the money? What magic made that happen? Okay, so one way
of understanding it is that he never owed Charlie the money. I
gave Charlie the right to collect the money that was owed to
me, but it's still owed to me. He's just now the person
who has the right for it to be transferred into his bank
account essentially. Okay? So like there's an automatic direct deposit thing going
on there but ultimately that's a personal thing between David and me,
he owes the money, that's one way of understanding it.
Okay, now, why we have to understand it that way or there's
another way of understanding it. Even if I sold him something, let's
say I had liens on David's property and I sold him those
liens, but those liens only made sense because they were a collection
of a debt, the debt still remains personal. So even though he
has those liens, as soon as I waive the debt, the liens
automatically disappear. So because of the personal nature of the debt and
it's not purely just financial, even once I sell it, it's still
money that's personally owed to me and therefore I can be מוחל
mochel it. Now, there is a discussion that sort of דיני דגרמי,
dinei d'garmi, if you remember that going back to the first half
of בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, that if you cause type of indirect
losses and injuries you have to compensate, but if I actually did
that Charlie could go ahead and sue me for causing him a
loss. Okay, but nevertheless in principle I could be מוחל mochel that.
Okay, so that's true. Since שמואל says ואפילו יורש מוחל, v'afilu yoresh
mochel, not only can the person who was originally owed the money
to be מוחל, mochel, even if he dies and now the money
is only owed to his heir, because then you would think it's
less personal now, the heir could also be מוחל mochel and the
person and the guy who bought the debt would be out the
money. So if that's true,
so why now can you, I'm now back to being the wife,
okay, why can I the wife not be told that look you
got to sell your stuff to Charlie there and use that money
to pay, to pay Frank who you injured. The reason is the
following, the reason I can't be forced to sell my כתובה ketubah
to pay somebody else is because why? Is because then what am
I going to do? I'm going to sell my כתובה, ketubah, pay
Frank, and then I'm going to turn around and be מוחל mochel
to my husband like money
since I'm no longer a beneficiary of the כתובה ketubah I'm going
to be מוחל mochel and Charlie is going to be out. So
the
גמרא Gemara says אמרי זבני ומה בכך, amri zavni u'mah bekach, and
so what? Let her sell it ותיתבי ליה, v'titevei leh, pay the
person she injured, ותמחול ליה לגבי בעל תמחול ליה, v'timchol leh legabei
baal timchol leh, and if she's מוחל mochel now the money owed
her, if she's מוחל mochel her husband the money owed because she
is not going to collect anymore, then let her do it, and
that'll be Charlie's problem, and Charlie will factor that into the price,
but it doesn't explain, there still is even with all these הלכות,
halachot, there still is a market for כתובות ketubot right now, so
let her sell her כתובה, ketubah, use the money to pay the
guy she injured, you still haven't answered the question. Yes, Charlie.
So two things, one is back to the issue of making it
difficult to divorce, that would seem to not apply to once רבנו
גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom said you can't get divorced without your permission.
That is true. The idea that a person can't remain without a
כתובה, ketubah, the רמ"א Rama says once there's תקנת רבנו גרשום takanat
Rabbeinu Gershom might not have the same impact that it used to
have, that's correct.
Second thing is this thing about
the
seller of a debt can still forgive the debt, that would wipe
out all the securitization debt.
I understand and I'll read a תוספות Tosafot in a minute. I
mean it's crazy. Now there might have been a way to do
it through מעמד שלשתן, maamad shloshtan, there might be ways to do
it that... To actually make it a full transfer. Okay, but yeah,
this הלכה Halacha is, right, it should destroy the market. Anyways, it
goes like this: Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, so anyway sell
it and let that be Charlie's problem. גמרא Gemara says, אמר ליה,
כולי לגבי בעל ודאי מחלה. Kulei legabei ba'al vadai machala. No, no,
no, because here it's not she would definitely be מוחלת, Mochelet, she's
still married to her husband, he had to sell it in order
to pay this guy she injured, so of course now she's not
gonna want her husband to have to pay the כתובה Ketubah to
Charlie. So she's of course gonna be מוחלת Mochelet so that the
husband, right? I mean it's her husband now, she cares more for
her husband than she does for Charlie. So of course she's gonna
keep gonna be מוחלת Mochelet to her husband. ולא פסידנא להו זוזי
בידיים לאפסידנא. Velo psideina lehu zuzei beyadayim le-afseidina.
Okay, and we're not going to actively as a court say to
her, in order to pay Frank you have to sell your כתובה
Ketubah to Charlie, if we know that we're giving Charlie a raw
deal. We know what's going to happen is she's going to be
מוחלת. Mochelet. So there's no way we would demand that. We'll say
she'll pay Frank when she gets divorced. We're not going to make
her pay Frank now in a way to hurt somebody else. וכי
תימא, Vekhi Teima, זבינה ניהליה לההוא דחבלה ביה בטובת הנאה. Zebinah nihaleih
le-hahu de-chabla beih be-tovat hana'ah. Wait, we got a solution.
Let us assess the value of the כתובה Ketubah and sell the
כתובה Ketubah not to Charlie, sell the כתובה Ketubah to Frank. Think
about it. I injured Frank for $100. Let's assume the טובת הנאה
Tovat Hana'ah of my כתובה Ketubah happens magically to be worth exactly
$100. So I say here we are, I will now give you
my כתובה Ketubah rights. Okay, I pay that to Frank. You're paid
off for the money I owe you. What could happen? I could
turn around and be מוחלת Mochelet to my husband. Okay, and in
that case, it turns out that I didn't give him anything, it
turns out I didn't pay him. Oh, in that case, after I
get divorced I'm going to have to pay him anyway. So it's
like either way Frank is going to get his money. I give
him right now my כתובה Ketubah rights worth $100. If I'm not
מוחלת Mochelet to my husband, okay, and then he's been paid up.
If I am מוחלת Mochelet to my husband and it turns out
I voided the whole thing that I became worthless what I gave
him, then I still have to pay him the $100 when I
get divorced. So why not do that? Why not have her transfer
her כתובה Ketubah rights to the person she injured? Okay, and that
way he might be paid now and if it turns out she's
מוחלת Mochelet and it and he wasn't paid now, he'll at least
be able to get paid later. You got the case? Yeah. Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara says, no. דאי מחלה לגבי בעל לא קא
מפסיד, De'i machala legabei ba'al lo ka mafsid, because in that case
if she gave the כתובה Ketubah rights to the person she injured,
if she has been מוחלת Mochelet the debt to her husband and
makes those rights worthless, לא קא מפסיד, Lo ka mafsid, the guy
isn't going to lose out. אשתקד נמי לא מידי הוה יהיב לה.
Eshtakad nami lo midi hava yahiv lah. At the end of the
day, he wasn't getting anything now anyway. Right? So as opposed to
right now we're telling him wait till she gets divorced or dies
or the husband dies, which might be he might be waiting fifty
years. So the alternative is, okay, get paid now with the
כתובה Ketubah rights and then you'll get some money in your pocket
or you'll get some value in your pocket right now, and if
it turns out that something bad happens with that, that she's מוחלת
Mochelet or whatever, you'll then you'll get paid later. But there's a
possibility you're getting paid right now. So isn't that better? So the
גמרא Gemara says,
no. סוף סוף כולי לגבי בעל ודאי מחלה. Sof sof kulei legabei
ba'al vadai machala. No, no, no, because we know in that case
also she'll be מוחלת Mochelet to her husband. וטרחא דבי דינא בכדי
לא מטרחינן. Ve-tarchah de-vei dina be-khadi lo matrachinan.
And we're not going to make בית דין Beit Din have to
go to this effort for naught. Okay, so bottom line is he's
not going to get anything now, okay? And he'll get something, it'll
look like he's getting paid now, but we know she's going to
be מוחלת. Mochelet. So what's the point? So let's just step back
and say what have we and we're not going to make בית
דין Beit Din go through this process if there's not going to
really be any benefit. So what's the point? The point is like
this: Why does this woman have no money to give the guy?
Doesn't she have her נכסי מלוג? Nikhsei Melog? And the answer is
no, she doesn't because after well, this is a proof of תקנת
אושא. Takanat Usha. You see she can't transfer her נכסי מלוג. Nikhsei
Melog. So that's why she has no money to give the guy.
So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, even if she can't transfer
title to any of this stuff, let her sell the טובת הנאה,
Tovat Hana'ah, let her sell the possibility of collecting it in the
future. And the גמרא Gemara says no because since there's שמואל'ס Shmuel's
הלכה Halacha that she could be מוחלת, Mochelet, that would we would
be forcing a sale that would hurt the person who would purchase
it. And even if she were to give it, pay, use it
to pay the guy she injured, we would say we know that
that would become worthless. And since we know she would be מוחלת
Mochelet and it would become worthless, there is no point of making
her raise cash through selling this because it's just going to hurt
other people. Okay, so she can't give actual title because of תקנת
אושא, Takanat Usha, she can't sell the right to it because the
person who gets that right is just going to be holding a,
you know, a bag of goods as we say, like they're going
to be holding something worthless and we're not going and we're not
going to do that. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. אלא הא דתניא, Ela ha de-tanya, that which we taught in
a ברייתא, Baraita, וכן היא שחבלה בבעלה. Ve-khen hi she-chabla be-ba'alah. בעלה
לא הפסידה כתובתה. baalah lo hifsi'dah kesuvaseha.
Let's say she injured her husband, okay, she does not lose her
כתובה. kesuvah. And here actually it says one minute if she injured
her husband, she should have
a way she can pay her husband, basically sell her husband back
her כתובה. kesuvah. So if the, you know, if all of this,
this might be worth probably worth $10,000,
but if the market value based on the risk that it'll ever
get paid out, you know,
becomes is $3,000, and
so let her basically say, fine, you'll never have to pay me
my כתובה kesuvah and I'm paying you up your $3,000 that I
owe you. That makes a lot of sense. Because what could she
do? מוחל mochal to her husband? That's what she effectively just did
right now. She was מוחל mochal to her husband. She basically freed
her husband from this debt, okay, from this possible future payout by
and that's value paid up the value of the חבלה. chavalah. So
why is it, why do we say that she doesn't have to
do that? וכן היא שחבלה בבעלה לא הפסידה כתובתה, ve'chen hee she'chavlah
b'baalah lo hifsi'dah kesuvaseha, אמאי, amai, why is that true? תזבנינה לההיא
לכתובתה לבעלה בטובת הנאה, tizveninah l'halay l'kesuvaseha l'baalah b'tovas hana'ah,
let her sell it to her husband with טובת הנאה, tovas hana'ah,
the current value of the כתובה, kesuvah, okay,
בהאי חבלה b'hai chavalah in order for, in order to pay off
the injury. ואי מחלה, ve'ee mochlah,
and if she is מוחל, mochal, I mean what do you mean
מוחל? mochal? Now the husband's going to pay out and collect his
his own payout? So לגבי בעל הכל בסדר, l'gabi baal hakol b'seder,
he's not losing out, right? Because effectively she was מוחל mochal it
right now. She basically said, you know, forget about ever having to
pay out the כתובה, kesuvah, that's how much is that worth to
you, $3,000?
Fine, now I've paid up your כתובה, kesuvah, your the the injury.
So why not? ומשני u'meshani הא רבי מאיר היא. ha Rabbi Meir
hee. That is רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, דאמר אסור לאדם שישהה עם
אשתו אפילו שעה אחת בלא כתובה. d'amar assur l'adam she'yesheha im ishto
afilu sha'ah achas b'lo kesuvah. Now, that is רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir,
because if you sold your כתובה kesuvah to somebody else, that רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir could live with, because the husband would eventually have
to pay out the money, whether to the wife or to somebody
else. But if you're selling your כתובה kesuvah back to your husband
to pay money you owe your husband, then after that, okay, the
injury got paid up, but now, he's not out any money, now
there's nothing stopping him from divorcing his wife. So in for that,
you're not allowed to do, because then you're going to have a
situation where there's no כתובה kesuvah to be paid up. So the
גמרא Gemara says one minute, even if she wouldn't have done that,
the husband wouldn't lose any money. טעמא מאי, taama mai, what's the
reason that you're not allowed to have a marriage without a
כתובה? kesuvah? כדי שלא תהא קלה בעיניו להוציאה, kedei she'lo tehei kalah
b'einav l'hotzi'ah, so that
he won't be easy in his eyes to
divorce
her. So הכא מגרשה וגבי לה בחבלה מיניה. hacha megarshah u'gavei lah
b'chavalah minei. So so so the גמרא Gemara, says,
so you have the same problem if she didn't sell it back
to him. Once there's this debt that she owes him, there's nothing
that's going to stop him from divorcing her, because he'll divorce her
and then take the money back the injury that she owes him.
So the גמרא Gemara says, so אי הכי, ee hachi, says the
גמרא, Gemara השתא נמי מגרשה וגבי לה בחבלה מיניה. hashta nami megarshah
u'gavei lah b'chavalah minei. So the גמרא Gemara says, one minute,
השתא נמי מגרשה וגבי לה בחבלה מיניה. hashta nami megarshah u'gavei lah
b'chavalah minei. So אי הכי, ee hachi,
I guess the first one was, you know, here he can divorce
her and he's not going to have to pay because the money's
already been paid out for the injury, that's if she sold it
back to him. So if it's so, and therefore it won't stop
him. So the גמרא Gemara says, השתא נמי, hashta nami, so even
if she didn't sell it back to him, מגרשה וגבי לה בחבלה
מיניה, megarshah u'gavei lah b'chavalah minei, let him there's nothing to stop
him from divorcing her, he'll divorce her, pay out the money, and
then collect it back. So the גמרא Gemara says no, there's an
obvious answer to this. דנפיש כתובתה, d'nafish kesuvaseha, no
no no, again, give the scenario I gave. The scenario I gave,
the כתובה kesuvah is worth $10,000,
the injury was $3,000.
If she, but that's also the טובת הנאה tovas hana'ah of the
כתובה kesuvah is $3,000. So if right now she says to her
husband, right, I owe you $3,000, forget it, you'll never have to
pay me the כתובה, kesuvah, we'll call it even, then there's there's
no loss for the husband to divorce his wife, right? Because he's
now there's now if he divorces her, it's going to be no
money out of pocket. But let's say she didn't do that. She
had an outstanding debt of $3,000. What's going to stop him from
divorcing his wife now? Because if he divorces his wife, how much
is he going to have to pay her? $10,000, right? So you
see, so so therefore if he actually liquidates her כתובה, kesuvah, sells
it right now with the טובת הנאה, tovas hana'ah, then there's then
he owes her nothing, and there's nothing going to stop her. But
if she owes him $3,000 and the כתובה kesuvah is $10,000, then
that'll stop him from divorcing her because he doesn't want to have
to pay the difference. Is that clear? Yeah? All right. So the
גמרא Gemara says like
this, אלא דנפיש כתובתה, ela d'nafish kesuvaseha, the
כתובה kesuvah is more than the cost of the injury. because of
that little bit that he's going to get back to the injury,
he's not going to want to have to pay out the full
כתובה. ksuva. So we don't force her, so if she injures her
husband, we don't force her to sell her כתובה ksuva back to
her husband, because then she'll have no כתובה ksuva and there'll be
nothing protecting her, and she'll have to sell it at less than
the face value, right, because it's not payable now. Rather, she owes
the money, the כתובה ksuva still retains its face value, and then
the husband is going to hesitate to divorce her because he's not
going to want to pay the difference between the injury amount and
the face value of the כתובה. ksuva. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says
yes, this is as long as the injury amount is less, right.
If the injury amount was more than the face value of the
כתובה, ksuva, maybe we would make her. Of course, then how would
we let them remain married is not clear. So, okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says ואי דנפישה כתובתה מכתובה דאורייתא, ve-ee denafisha ksuvassa miksuva
de-oraisa, the גמרא Gemara says one minute, wait, I gotta wait to
make this work even in your scenario. If the כתובה ksuva is
worth more than the total, when רבי מאיר Rav Meir says you
cannot live without a כתובה, ksuva, the only amount רבי מאיר Rav
Meir is talking about that you absolutely, what halachically is absolutely required,
is
this
amount, the
base 200 amount
of the כתובה. ksuva.
And that's only for a woman who's never been married,
right, or 100 for a woman who's been married. So the גמרא
Gemara says I still don't get it, why not force her to
sell back to her husband the other parts of the כתובה? ksuva?
Okay, keep the 200 that the husband owes her, so you're satisfying
the halachic requirement, but to pay off for the injury of the
husband, sell back the other parts of the כתובה. ksuva. So the
גמרא Gemara says ואי דנפישה כתובתה מכתובה דאורייתא, ve-ee denafisha ksuvassa miksuva
de-oraisa, if כתובה ksuva is more than the biblical amount, נוקים כתובה
דאורייתא, nokim ksuva de-oraisa,
keep the כתובה ksuva the biblical part of it, don't sell back
that back to the husband, ואידך תזבניה ניהליה בחבליה, ve-idach tizbenih niharai
be-chavlai, sell back to the husband for the amount of the injury.
So the
גמרא says no, כגון דלא נפישה כתובתה מכתובה דאורייתא. ke-gon delo nafisha
ksuvassa miksuva de-oraisa. Fine, you're right, in that case she would have
to sell the rest back to her husband. But we're talking about
a case where she only has a base כתובה ksuva of 200.
And she only has the base כתובה ksuva of 200, you can't
force her to sell that back to her husband, not only can't
you force, you're not allowed to, because she needs to retain her
base כתובה. ksuva. והא, ve-ha,
now what would be a case, דהוי חבליה ארבע זוזי, de-havei chavlei
arba zuzei,
let's say the injury was ארבע זוזי, arba zuzei, must have been
a very minor injury.
דמשום ארבע זוזי לא מפסיד עשרים וחמישה, de-mishum arba zuzei lo mafsid
esrim ve-chamisha,
she wouldn't lose 25. Now what does 25 mean? Isn't it 100
or 200? רש"י Rashi says it's 25, you
know, סלע, sela, which is 100 זוז. zuz. There's like a four-to-one
ratio and we're talking about a כתובה ksuva on an אלמנה. almanah.
Now why we're talking about a כתובה ksuva on an אלמנה almanah
and not a כתובה ksuva on a בתולה besulah of 200? Okay,
I won't worry you about all the coinage here, okay. But anyway
the point is that the כתובה ksuva is only 200, there's none
of this extra stuff, and we don't make her give up, cut
into her, or give
up/cut into/slash give up her full כתובה דאורייתא. ksuva de-oraisa. Not only
don't we make her, we wouldn't allow her, because she can't be
with her husband without at least the base כתובה. ksuva. And she
just owes the money,
fine. אלא one more case about this, הא דתניא, had de-sanya, that
which we taught in a ברייתא. Baraisa. כשם שלא תמכור היא לאחרים,
keshem she-lo timkor hi le-acharim, the same way, or it's like תוספות
Tosafos reads it, she does not sell her כתובה ksuva to other
people if she owes/injured somebody else, she doesn't sell her כתובה ksuva
to pay this other person. כך לא תפסיד היא לבעלה, kach lo
tafsid hi le-vahlah, she doesn't lose her כתובה ksuva to her husband
and you know, if she injured her husband, that's how תוספות Tosafos
reads it. Okay, so similar thing that we saw, she doesn't sell
her כתובה ksuva back to her husband. So the גמרא says one
minute, זימנין דמשתכחא דמפסדא, zimnin de-mishtakcha de-mafseda, there are times that she
would actually lose her כתובה. ksuva. What is it? והיכי דמי ve-heichi
dami like we said, כגון דנפישה כתובתה מכתובה דאורייתא. ke-gon de-nafisha ksuvassa
miksuva de-oraisa.
If you have the, if the כתובה ksuva is more than the
biblical amount, have pieces to it and she injured her husband, then
she would have to sell that amount back to her husband in
order to pay off the debt she owes her husband. So אמר
רבא, Amar Rava, רבא Rava said fine, you're right, that is true.
If there was more to the כתובה ksuva than the 200 and
she injured her husband, she'd have to sell that amount back to
her husband. But the end of this ברייתא Baraisa means something else.
סיפא אתיין לכתובת בנין דכרין, seifa asyan licksurvas banin dichrin,
the end is talking about a case of the כתובה ksuva of
male sons. What is the כתובה ksuva of male sons? What that
means is that the woman brings all this property into the marriage.
If she dies first, her husband's going to inherit her, okay. Then
where's that property going to go to? All of his children, which
might not all be her children. Now she does not want the
property she
brought in
to
stay... I went ahead and I sold my כתובה Kesubah to Charlie.
Okay, now Charlie's only going to collect that כתובה Kesubah if my
husband dies first or I get divorced, right? You're with me, right?
If I die first, okay, that's never any money I would have
collected, so Charlie gets nothing. So my selling that כתובה Kesubah to
Charlie does not impact the fact that if I die first, the
בנין דכרין Benin Dichrin part of my כתובה Kesubah remains valid, because
Charlie's only rights to the כתובה Kesubah were in cases where my
husband divorced me or my husband died first, okay? So בנין דכרין
Benin Dichrin obviously are not impacted when I sell my כתובה Kesubah
to Charlie. You understand there are different scenarios. Charlie gets it when
my husband dies first, בנין דכרין Benin Dichrin are when I die
first, okay? So כשם שמוכרת כתובתה לאחרים ולא הפסידה כתובת בנין דכרין.
Keshem Shemoches Kesuvoso Leacherim Velo Hisidda Kesubas Benin Dichrin. מאי טעמא? Mai
Taama? זוזי הוא דאנסוה, Zuze Hu De'antsuha, because I was just doing
selling it because I was forced by money to sell to Charlie
and it did not mean that I was giving up the other
rights of my כתובה, Kesubah,
so, right, well, just because I sold it to Charlie because I
needed cash doesn't mean because I was giving up the rights... I'm
sorry to the wife. בנין דכרין Benin Dichrin מאי טעמא mai taama
אנסוה דהא לאשה antsuha deha la'isha because it doesn't mean just because
I needed the cash I was giving up the other rights of
my כתובה Kesubah that were not related to me selling it to
Charlie. So כך מוכרת כתובתה לבעלה Kach Moches Kesuvoso Laba'al
similarly, if a woman had to sell, not because of injury, for
whatever reason, she sold her כתובה Kesubah back to her husband, we'll
ignore רבי מאיר'ס Rabbi Meir's concerns for a moment, okay? She sold
her כתובה Kesubah back to her husband. What when she was selling
it here's an interesting question. When she was selling it back to
her husband, so certainly she was telling her husband you're not going
to have to pay out if I die first or if you
divorce me. Was she also forfeiting the right that her male children
would collect her portion if she died first? Do you understand the
question? What is the husband buying back? Okay, it's a good question.
A third party is only buying the cases the things that would
happen if she died first. Well, when the husband is buying it
back, maybe he's buying back all of the rights, and maybe he's
even buying back בנין דכרין. Benin Dichrin. It says no, he's not
buying back בנין דכרין. Benin Dichrin. כך מוכרת כתובתה לבעלה לא הפסידה
כתובת בנין דכרין. Kach Moches Kesuvoso Laba'al Lo Hisidda Kesubas Benin Dichrin.
He does not lose that. מאי טעמא? Mai Taama? זוזי הוא דאנסוה.
Zuze Hu De'antsuha. She's just hard up for cash and that means
that she's willing to give up what she would have collected. All
of this in cases she would have collected it, she's willing to
give that up. But in cases where she would have died first,
but she's not willing to give up stuff that would have been
really even been for her children, and that we don't assume that
she's selling, okay? So we'll end with that and we'll wrap up
tomorrow with the discussion of finalizing the whole discussion of תקנת אושא.
Takkanas Usha.